Have you ever looked back on
an event in your life and
wished it went differently?
Well, we can't help
you go back in time,
but there are things you
can do to ensure you
don't experience the
same missteps again.
In the last video,
we discussed continuous
improvements.
One way to ensure
continuous improvements is
to conduct a retrospective,
so let's discuss that a
little more in depth.
A retrospective is a
workshop or meeting
that gives project teams time
to reflect on a project.
Retrospectives, sometimes
known as retros,
should happen throughout
the life cycle
of a project, but mostly
are implemented after
major milestones,
or most commonly, after
a project is completed.
Retrospectives give you a
chance to discuss successes
and setbacks that took
place within the
project or phases.
You can think of
them as a form of
process improvement
within your project.
Retrospectives serve
three main purposes:
First, they encourage
team building,
because they allow team
members to understand
different perspectives
within their team.
Second, they facilitate
improved collaboration
on future projects.
Third, they promote
positive changes
in future procedures
and processes.
Let's detail each one.
Retrospectives are great for
team-building since they
enable teams to understand
each other better and facilitate
better collaboration, which
improves productivity.
The emphasis in retrospectives is
on continuous improvement
and change,
instead of recycling old—
and potentially bad—habits,
procedures, and processes.
Retrospectives are
helpful because
even if we plan for
every possible risk,
odds are that something
will sneak up on us.
When something does fall through
the cracks and you need to
reflect on it with the team,
you may want to conduct
a retrospective.
Some additional reasons that
you might want to conduct
a retrospective include missed
deadlines or expectations,
or miscommunications
between stakeholders.
You may also want to hold
a retrospective at
the end of a sprint.
As a reminder, a sprint is
a series of ordered
tasks ending in a goal.
You could also hold
a retrospective
after product launches
and landings.
These are all great opportunities
to record key lessons that
other people might learn from as
they work on their own projects.
Identifying the stumbling
blocks and successes in
a project helps improve
future processes,
but the way you decide to
conduct a retrospective can vary.
There's no exact formula or
template for a productive
retrospective;
the way you choose to structure
your retrospective will depend
on your team and workplace.
You may decide to
conduct a formal,
in-person retrospective
if your team
prefers to debrief
in that setting.
You can incorporate sticky notes,
documents, or any other kind of
physical tools to help
your team debrief.
Or if you find that
your team often
gets off track during
in-person meetings,
you may decide a virtual
or online retrospective
is a better option.
In this case, surveys
might help to get
thoughts organized.
Although there's no one way
to conduct retrospectives,
there are certain best
practices to keep in mind.
As we previously mentioned,
you'll want your retrospectives
to be blameless.
Making sure that everyone
feels comfortable
giving feedback as
candidly as possible will
result in the most
productive retrospective.
To navigate through
awkward situations
or sensitive subjects,
it may be necessary to encourage
anonymous or private feedback.
A couple of tactics
a project manager
can use to ensure
the process remains
blameless are changing
perspective and
switching from "you"
language to "we" language.
Changing perspective
means putting
yourself in someone else's shoes.
If your team is quick to blame
the delivery company for
their plants not arriving at
the customer's office on time,
think about the situation from
the delivery company's
perspective.
Was the delivery company's route
optimized and tested
to avoid traffic?
If not, maybe that should have
been a task in your project.
Using "you" language can get
you in trouble because it can
feel like everyone in the room is
judging the person
receiving the blame.
For example, telling your
project's sponsor that
"You didn't make it clear
that we didn't have money
for a contingency
budget when plants die"
is not as productive as saying
"The lack of a contingency budget
wasn't made fully clear from
the get-go, and that's
something that we can
improve upon for next time."
The project sponsor may feel
attacked and wonder why you,
the project manager, didn't ask
the right questions
in the early stages.
Maybe the fact of the matter
is that both of you
could have done a little
bit more to include
a contingency budget,
and that's okay.
Make sure you aren't only
focusing on the negative.
Retrospectives are
about reflecting on
the positive aspects
of projects too,
so talk about what went
well. What was fun?
What new things
will you be able to
carry with you into
future projects?
Maybe the sales and
marketing teams
don't work together often,
but this gave them an
opportunity to bond.
Maybe you enjoyed working with
the Project Plant Pals contracted
website designer so
much that the team
has decided to hire
them full-time.
Whatever the positives were,
they're worth celebrating.
You could even order some dinner
or dessert as a thank
you to everyone.
Finally, you'll want to make sure
that you enact the
changes you've discussed.
You'll put the discussed
changes in place and
decide to handle the project a
little differently
in the next phase.
People don't want
to participate in
retrospectives if they
feel their feedback
isn't fully taken into
consideration and implemented.
Now that you have a general
overview for retrospectives,
we'll build upon this
foundation in the next video,
where we'll demonstrate
how to conduct
your own retrospective.
Meet you there.